[Music]
button
Professor Dave and Chegg here an
interesting aspect of organic molecules
is that they can join together to form
polymers these are long chain-like
molecules consisting of many repeats of
a small subunit called a monomer let's
learn about these now the best way to
learn about polymers is by examining the
different types of polymers so that we
can see the monomers they are comprised
of and how they link together ethene can
polymerize to form polyethylene this is
just thousands of fully saturated ch2
units perpetuating like a never-ending
straight chain alkane this substance is
a flexible plastic with many
applications if we replace the hydrogen
atoms on ethene with fluorine atoms and
then allow this to polymerize we get a
material called Teflon this is what
gives certain containers their non-stick
coating because the CF bonds are quite
inert
they are almost entirely unreactive
making the material tough and
non-flammable here is a table depicting
many other synthetic polymers according
to the monomers they are comprised of
some of them may sound familiar and
their applications will certainly be
familiar as these materials are
ubiquitous
polymerization can occur by a variety of
mechanisms sometimes they go by addition
polymerization which is a radical
mechanism meaning that it employs
radical intermediates which have
unpaired electrons another mechanism is
condensation polymerization where each
time two monomers are joint a water
molecule is lost a homopolymer is one in
which there is only one repeating
monomeric Unit A copolymer is one in
which there are two different monomers
that must combine to form the chain
nylon is an example of a copolymer
polyethylenes are some of the most
important polymers and there are two
forms low density polyethylene or ldpe
and high density polyethylene or HDPE
the low density variety is as such
because of the extensive branching which
causes the molecule to not be able to
pack together as tightly as for the high
density variety which is comprised
predominantly of straight chain
molecules with these compounds if a
substituent is present like this methyl
group this can result in an isotactic
chain where the methyl groups are all on
the same side of the molecule or an
atactic chain where they alternate from
one side to the other as is depicted
with these Dash and wedge bonds if the
substituent is a chlorine atom we get
polyvinyl chloride or PVC if the
substituent is a phenyl group meaning a
Benzene ring we get polystyrene if
styrene monomers are combined with some
other monomer to make a copolymer we can
get a variety of other useful polymers
with various applications
with that we have taken a glimpse into
the Incredible World of polymers which
have transformed the way we make
industrial materials Professor Dave for
Chegg see you next time
all right
foreign